Guide to the Paul Kagan Photographs of Utopian Communities and Personal Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs of Utopian Communities, 1968-1976; Series I; 3.38; (19 boxes)
  - Copy Photographs
    Source individuals and repositories are identified in most cases. Consult New World Utopias for descriptions of many of the images.
    Arranged alphabetically by site or individual and then chronologically, followed by various photographs from Kagan's personal collection and from unidentified sources.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Reference use only: photographs and negatives in this subseries may not be reproduced.
    - Fountaingrove, circa 1973; (2 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 225)
    - Icaria Speranza
      - Robert V. Hine, circa 1971; (1 negative) (Box 18, Folder 226)
      - Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1972 January-circa 1973; (14 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 227-228)
      - Ernest Leroy Marchand (1898-1985), circa 1973; (14 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 229)
    - Kaweah Colony
      - Bancroft Library, 1971 January; (109 negatives and 2 photographic prints) (Box 18, Folder 230)
    - Krotona and Happy Valley School
      - Betty Robertson Warrington, 1972 February; (48 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 231)
        - Oversize Prints of Krotona, 1972 February; (12 photographic prints) (Box 17, Folder 232)
          From origial photographs owned by Warrington.
      - Rosalind Edith Rajagopal, 1972 February 21; (16 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 18, Folder 233)
      - Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, circa 1972; (5 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 234)
      - Jack Rainey, circa 1972; (24 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 18, Folder 235)
    - Llano Del Rio and Newllano
      - California Historical Society, 1975; (42 negatives and 1 contact sheet) (Box 18, Folder 236)
        Includes maps of California.
    - Pisgah Faith Home and Pisgah Grande
      - Harold James Smith, circa 1972; (63 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 237)
        Reverend Harold James Smith (died 1994) was director from 1950-1993 of Christ Faith Mission Inc., which purchased the Pisgah Faith Home after 1920.
        Includes portraits of Smith in front of the Pisgah Faith Home
      - University of California, Los Angeles, circa 1972; (6 negatives) (Box 18, Folder 238)
    - Point Loma
      - Bancroft Library, 1972 January; (112 negatives and 10 contact sheets) (Box 19, Folder 239)
      - Iverson L. Harris, 1972 February; (54 negatives, 3 contact sheets, and 9 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 240)
        Includes portraits by of Kagan of Harris' sister-in-law.
      - Judith M. Tyberg, 1972 February; (36 negatives and 3 contact sheets) (Box 19, Folder 241)
      - California Western University, circa 1972; (60 negatives and 5 contact sheets) (Box 19, Folder 242)
      - Emmett Greenwalt, circa 1972; (1 negative) (Box 19, Folder 243)
      - San Diego Public Library, circa 1972; (24 negatives and 2 contact sheets) (Box 19, Folder 244)
      - University of California, San Diego, circa 1972; (60 negatives and 5 contact sheets) (Box 19, Folder 245)
    - Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, circa 1972; (16 negatives) (Box 19, Folder 246)
    - Various images from Kagan's personal collection of utopian material, circa 1972; (8 negatives) (Box 19, Folder 247-248)
    - View of an apartment building, circa 1975; (1 photographic print) (Box 19, Folder 249)
- Other Material Related to Utopian Communities, circa 1895-circa 1989; Series II; 0.52; (2 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
  This series is organized into two subseries: Audiotapes and Material Related to Utopian Communities.
  This series mainly consists of materials collected by Kagan related to utopian communities, as well as his own work with traditional and alternative newspapers, and social action activities in and around the University of California, Berkeley, and the San Francisco Bay area.
  - Audiotapes, 1964-1977; (7 audiotapes)
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available in the same box as original tapes. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Reel-to-reel recordings made by of Kagan of interviews and events chiefly related to utopian communities, as well as recordings of dialogues between Jiddu Krishnamurti and Jacob Needleman (born 1934) distributed by the Krishnamurti Foundation.
    Descriptions taken from the original boxes that housed the tapes.
    - Interviews and Events, 1964-1976 January; 1; 12:28:48; The program is distorted at times. There is high background noise on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398504)
      There are several recordings listed for this audiotape reel.
      Utopias
      Art Wadsworth interview of Leander Walter Millsap, Jr. (1886-1971), also known as Walter Millsap, of Llano Del Rio, California, 1964.
      Betty Robertson Warrington at Krotona in Ojai, California, 1971.
      Franklin Lacey, Director of the Happy Valley School, Ojai, California, January 25, 1971.
      Betty Robertson Warrington and Catherine Mayes at Krotona in Ojai, California, January 25, 1971.
      Mellie M. Calvert, a research assistant on Llano Del Rio, California, June 5, 1975.
      Address by Robert Hine at the opening of "New World Utopias: The Search for Community in the West, 1876-1975," at the Oakland Museum of California, August 18, 1975
      Robert Ellwood (born 1933), a professor of world religions at the University of Southern California, January 18, 1971
      John Farquhar, Vedanta Temple, Santa Barbara, January 26, 1971
      Iverson Louis Harris, Point Loma, California, June 4-5, 1975
      Group Discussion between Kagan and others, The Farm, Summertown, Tennessee, January 17, 1976
      Wedding at The Farm, Summertown, Tennessee, January 17, 1976
      Stephen Gaskin, The Farm, Summertown, Tennessee, January 18, 1976
    - Interviews, 1971 January 29-1975 May 23; 1; 07:28:42; The program is distorted at times. There is high background noise on the recording. The program ends abruptly. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398512)
      Recordings found on this audiotape reel are listed below.
      John Bartlmain, Pisgah Grande, California, January 29, 1971.
      Harold James Smith, Christ Faith Mission Inc., Los Angeles, California, January 29, 1971.
      Peter Mollica, artist specializing in stained glass windows, 1972.
      Koski Ijichi, Fountaingrove, California, 1975. Irvin Fisher, Holy City, California, 1975.
      Gaye le Baron, Fountaingrove, California, May 23, 1975.
    - Interviews, 1971 January 20-1975 June; 1; 08:28:40; There is high background noise on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398520)
      Recordings on this audiotape reel are listed below.
      Judith M. Tyberg at the East-West Cultural Center in Los Angeles, California, January 20, 1971.
      Swami Sri Ananda Prana, at Vedanta Temple, Hollywood, January 21, 1971.
      John Way, Fellowship Farms, January 23, 1971.
      Woman at Pisgah Faith Home, January 23, 1971.
      Langmuir at Vedanta, January 23, 1971.
      Rosalind Edith Rajagopal, Franklin Lacey, Mrs. Ragan and Beatrice Wood? at Happy Valley School, Ojai, California, January 24, 1971.
      Art Wadsworth, teacher at Happy Valley School, Ojai, California, January 24, 1971
      Happy Valley School, Ojai, California, June 1975.
      Betty Robertson Warrington and Catherine Mayes at Krotona in Ojai, California, June 1975.
    - Talks and Radio - Utopias / J. G. Bennet (?), Navajo Interview, 1971 February 22-1977 July 4; 1; 09:31:52; The audio fades in and out. There is high background noise on tape. The program is distorted at times. The program was recorded over a previously recorded program. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398538)
      A list of recordings are included with this audiotape reel.
      Kagan speaking with Bennett Berger (1926-2005) and a sociology seminar at University of California, Davis, February 22, 1971.
      Kagan talk on communes, April 25, 1974. Excerpts from discussion of John G. Bennett (1897-1974) and a Transcendental Meditation Group in Los Angeles, California, on KQED-FM, San Francisco, California, which included a review of New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community, July 1975.
      Kagan interviewed by Wes "Scoop" Nisker on KSAN-FM, San Mateo, California, August 1975.
      Interview by KQED-FM, San Francisco, California, with Kagan and others, including Ann Hawkon, Paul Hawkon, Will Hoffke, and Mike Gratts, September 13, 1975.
      Paul Rosenblum, Green Gulch Farm Zen Center, also known as Green Dragon Temple (Soryu-ji), Muir Beach, California, February 8, 1976.
      Navajo Indian, possibly spiritual leader Tommy Nez (1926-2010), in Gallup, New Mexico, July 4, 1977.
    - J. Krishnamurti and Jacob Needleman Dialogue #1 (Ojai, California: Krishnamurti Foundation), 1971 March; 1; 00:47:12; There is static on the tape. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398546)
    - J. Krishnamurti and Jacob Needleman Dialogue #2 (Ojai, California: Krishnamurti Foundation), 1971 March; 1; 00:50:43 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398553)
    - Paul Kagan, Master Voice Over for "New World Utopias: The Search for Community in the West, 1876-1975", 1975 June; 1; 02:27:05; The program is distorted at times. There is static on the tape and high background noise. The program ends abruptly. (Box 20, Item barcode 39002091398561)
  - Material Related to Utopian Communities
    - Drawings of Fountaingrove by an unidentified artist, circa 1895; (8 drawings) (Box 21, Folder 257-259)
      Disbound sketchbook that depicts the interior of the Round Barn, another building, and landscapes.
    - Photograph of a pottery display created at Halcyon, circa 1910 (Box 21, Folder 260)
    - Photograph of a man cutting marble for Point Loma, circa 1909 (Box 21, Folder 261)
    - Photograph of a creek by Harold A. Parker, 1911 (Box 21, Folder 262)
      Harold A. Parker (1878-1930) was a professional photographer active in Pasadena, California, 1900-1930.
    - Photographic portrait of an Asian American woman, circa 1911 (Box 21, Folder 263)
    - Photographs of the Krotona Inn by the Arts and Crafts Guild, circa 1913; (7 photographic prints) (Box 21, Folder 264-270)
      The Arts and Crafts Guild was a group of artisans and photographers working within the Krotona colony in Hollywood, California.
      Photographs of the Krotona Inn (also known as Krotona Court) was built in Hollywood, California, in 1912-1913.
    - Hand-tinted photographs of the Krotona Inn and Grand Temple of the Rosy Cross, circa 1914; (3 photographic prints) (Box 21, Folder 271)
      Grand Temple of the Rosy Cross, built 1914, was an auditorium of the Krotona Colony.
    - Lama Foundation, Poster with a figure of an angel and child, 1968 (Box bsd, folder 272)
    - Divine Light Mission (Divya Sandesh Parishad), Poster advertising a lecture by Prem Rawat (born 1957, also known as Maharaj Ji and Balyogeshwar), 1972 September (Box bsd, folder 273)
      The Divine Light Mission (Divya Sandesh Parishad) was an organization founded in 1960 by Shri Hans Ji Maharaj (1900-1966). It gained prominence under the leadership of his fourth and youngest son, Prem Rawat.
    - Clipping, Lillian M. Snyder, "Icarian Emigration to Nauvoo Outlined" in Macomb Daily Journal (Macomb, Illinois), 1971 March 11 (Box 21, Folder 274)
      Lillian M. Snyder (1914-2005) was a descendent Emile Baxter (died 1895), who was a member of the Board of Directors and Secretary of the first chartered Icarian colony in Nauvoo, Illinois.
    - California Historical Courier (San Francisco: California)
      - Volume 26, No. 7, 1974 November (Box 21, Folder 275)
        Article, "Utopian Studies Center Planned for Next Year," discusses the establishment of the center with Kagan as its director.
      - Volume 27, No. 3, 1975 April (Box 21, Folder 276)
        Includes an advertisement for Kagan's New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community.
    - Tract for the Rosicrucian Fellowship, circa 1975 (Box 21, Folder 277)
    - Tearsheet, Paul Kagan, "Outside the Mainstream: Reports from Four Alternative Communities" America, circa 1976 (Box 21, Folder 278)
    - Humanities Network (San Francisco, California), Volume 3, No. 3, 1979 Fall (Box 21, Folder 279)
      Includes article by Kagan, "The Early Pursuit of Community in California."
- Personal Papers, 1960-circa 1989; Series III; 0.1; (1 box) + 1 broadside folder
  This series is organized into two subseries: Works by Kagan, and University of California, Berkeley, and the San Francisco Bay Area
  Examples of photographs and graphic design that Kagan created for alternative newspapers and music venues, primarily in the San Francisco Bay area of California, as well as book reviews he wrote for New York Times Book Review. It also includes material related to social action activities in and around the University of California, Berkeley, and the San Francisco Bay area.
  - Works by Kagan
    Arranged chronologically
    - Flier for concerts by Robbie Basho and John Fahey at The Jabberwock, Berkeley, California, created by Kagan and Tom Weller, 1966 December (Box 22, Folder 280)
    - City of San Francisco Oracle (San Francisco, California) Volume 1, No. 7, 1967 April; 2 copies (Box 22, Folder 281)
      Includes photographs by Kagan, including several depicting a conversation among of Allen Ginsberg (1926-1997), Timothy Leary (1920-1996), Gary Snyder (born 1930), and Alan Watts (1915-1973).
    - The Seed (Chicago, Illinois) Volume 1, No. 2, 1967 May (Box 22, Folder 282)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Cover photograph by Kagan of Allen Ginsberg with a child.
    - Flier for Rolling Renaissance: Photography San Francisco, 1945-1968, at Light Sound Dimension Gallery, San Francisco, California, 1968 June (Box 22, Folder 283)
      Flier that includes a photograph by Kagan of Allen Ginsberg with a child.
    - Berkeley Tribe (Berkeley, California) Volume 1, No. 3-6, 1968 July-August (Box 22, Folder 284-287)
      Issues that include photographs by Kagan.
    - Fusion (Boston, Massachusetts), 1969 July (Box 22, Folder 288)
      Cover photograph by Kagan.
    - Ya Mutha's Cunt (Berkeley?: California) No. 1, 1970 September (Box bsd, folder 289)
      Poster advertising activities of "People's Week," September 4-25, 1970, in the San Francisco Bay Area.
    - Berkeley Barb (Berkeley, California) Volume 11, No. 19, 1970 November (Box 22, Folder 290)
    - The Night Times (Berkeley, California) Volume 1, No. 5, 1971 October-November (Box 22, Folder 291)
      Includes photographs by Kagan of country rock band Commander Cody and His Lost Planet Airmen, as well as a view of the Fox Theater Oakland in Oakland, California.
    - New York Times Book Review
      Issues with book reviews by Kagan.
      - Review of Janwillem Van de Wetering, A Glimpse of Nothingness: Experiences in an American Zen Community (Boston: Houghton Mifflin St. Martin's Griffin, 1975)., 1975 June 29 (Box 22, Folder 292)
      - Review of June Sprigg, By Shaker Hands (New York: Knopf, 1975)., 1976 January 4 (Box 22, Folder 293)
    - Flier for Allen Cohen, The San Francisco Oracle, Facsimile Edition: The Psychedelic Newspaper of the Haight-Ashbury, 1966-1968 (Berkeley, California: Regent Press, 1991), circa 1989 (Box 22, Folder 294)
      Includes group portrait of Allen Ginsberg, Timothy Leary, Gary Snyder, and Alan Watts by Kagan.
  - University of California, Berkeley, and the San Francisco Bay Area
    - Independent Californian (Berkeley, California) Volume 1, No. 1, 1960 October 25 (Box 22, Folder 295)
      Independent newspaper created by former staff members of the Daily Californian student newspaper at University of California, Berkeley.
    - Student election materials for SLATE campaign, 1961 (Box 23, Folder 296)
      A group of student leaders organized SLATE in February 1958, which included former members of a campus political party, TASC (Towards an Active Student Community) and other previously unaffiliated students, and proposed they run as a "slate" for student government office.
    - Eugene Weiss, Report on Graffiti, 1961-1962 (Box 23, Folder 297)
      Study of graffiti written for an anthropology class. It discusses graffiti at the University of California, Berkeley, the National Autonomous University of Mexico, in elementary and secondary schools, in neighborhoods throughout San Francisco, and in jails.
    - Flier about Planning the 20th Reunion of the Free Speech Movement at University of California, Berkeley, circa 1985 (Box 23, Folder 298)